各位大人
My Lords,
我们现继续商讨伐法大策
we will now proceed with our plans for an invasion of France.
从拿下战略重镇布洛涅开始
We will start by the capture of the strategic town of Boulogne.
大人 若你仍心怀壮志 体格强健 能驰骋疆场
Your Grace, I shall appoint you commander of our armies,
我即命你为我军指挥
if you have the will and the stomach for the fight.
陛下 在下能获此等殊荣
Majesty, I can only thank God
再度征战沙场 荣耀加身 唯有感谢上苍
for the chance to win honour and glory in the field,
手握利剑削铁如泥 冲锋呐喊震聋发聩
for what man would not prefer to die
又有何人不愿血洒疆场以死誓忠
with a sword in his hand and a cry in his throat...
正是
Aye.
而非于英格兰软卧香塌浑浑噩噩了此残生
...rather than abed in England.
- 正是 - 同意
- Aye. - Aye!
诸位大人 我必须告知你们
My Lords, I must tell you
罗马皇帝特使 奈赫拉公爵
that a special envoy from the court of the Emperor,
将对我们进行非正式访问
the Duke of Najera, will pay us an unofficial visit,
庆祝我们结盟
in honour of our alliance.
此公爵是罗马皇帝最战绩灼灼的将军之一
The Duke is one of the Emperor's most successful generals.
他将先在此处受到萨里伯爵的接见
He should be first received here by the Earl of Surrey
然后再引至宫廷
and then brought to court.
我确信各位大人将以礼相待 令其宾至如归
I'm sure your lordships will welcome him as he deserves.
是的 陛下
Yes, your majesty.
我已立誓痛击法王迫其投降
I have vowed to bring King Francis into submission,
我将倾力而战兑现誓言
and I will fulfil this promise.
我此生以德服人荣光无上
I have been all my life a prince of virtue and honour,
诸位皆可作证
as you can all attest,
我永不食言
and I have never contravened my word.
虽然如今我年老力衰难以为继
I'm too old to begin now.
我 凯瑟琳
I, Catherine
请你 亨利 做我的丈夫
take thee, Henry, to be my wedded husband,
从今日往后
to have and to hold from this day forward,
不论顺境或是逆境 富裕或是贫穷
for better, for worse, for richer, for poorer,
健康或是疾病
in sickness and in health,
我们都风雨同舟 患难与共 同甘共苦
to be bonaire and buxom in bed and at board,
相濡以沫 永不分离
till death us do part,
我愿与你结为连理
and thereto I plight thee my troth.
拿戒指来
The ring.
在天的主为我们见证
Benedicat, hic anulum, dominus, qui fecit caelum et terram.
以此枚戒指为证 你我结为连理
With this ring, I thee wed.
只要我息尚存
With my body,
我将永远爱护珍惜你
I thee worship.
以圣父圣子圣灵的名义
In nomine Patris, et Filii, et Spiritus Sancti.
我宣布你们结为夫妻
I now pronounce thee man and wife.
谢谢 赫尔贝女士
Thank you, Lady Herbert.
陛下慢用
Majesty.
谢谢你
Sister.
陛下慢用
Your Majesty.
陛下 我有一言 不知当讲否
Your Majesty, if I may?
讲
Uh-huh.
我决意成为几位孩子的慈爱继母
I am determined to be a loving stepmother to your children.
当然 我与玛丽女士已相识多年
Of course, I have known the Lady Mary for years,
能与爱德华王子和伊丽莎白女士成为朋友
but it would now be my pleasure rather than
相对职责而言
my duty to make friends with the Prince Edward
我更愿意欣然接受
and the Princess Elizabeth.
若得陛下首肯
So with Your Majesty's permission
我想今后多邀他们进宫
I would like to invite them more often to court,
这不仅是我出于私心
not only for my sake
也是为了让他们能经常见到父亲
but so they might more often see their father.
我同意
You have my permission.
谢谢您
Thank you.
也许陛下也会同意
And perhaps Your Majesty might also agree
让伊丽莎白女士
to the Lady Elizabeth having
拥有一处固定住所 如同玛丽女士一样
permanent lodgings at court, like the Lady Mary?
也许吧 但我不愿
Perhaps. But I would not
我儿爱德华常常出入宫廷
like my son Edward to come to court too often,
以防他被传染疾病
for fear he may catch infection.
我为你准备了些礼物 随后便会送到
I have arranged for some gifts to be delivered to you.
希望你会喜欢
I hope you like them.
多谢陛下
Thank you.
不必客气
You're welcome.
公爵大人 试试这把
Try this one, Your Grace.
- 公爵大人 - 诸位大人
- Your Grace. - My Lords.
我很荣幸向诸位传达陛下的旨意
I am pleased to convey to you His Majesty's commissions.
托马斯大人 您将从布鲁塞尔被召回
Sir Thomas, you are recalled from Brussels
荣任海军上将一职
and are to be appointed Admiral of the Fleet.
至于萨里大人
My Lord Surrey, the King has seen fit
陛下将封你为陆军上将
to make you Marshal of the Field,
这可是至高无上的荣誉
a singular honour.
- 谢大人 - 我等何时起航
- Your Grace. - When do we sail?
只待陛下一声令下
As soon as the King commands.
托马斯大人
Sir Thomas...
听说令兄赫福特大人反对战争
...is it true that your brother Lord Hertford,
- 可有此事 - 确有此事 大人
- is against this war? - It is true, Your Grace.
他担心陛下龙体欠安
He worries for the King's health,
并且心病成疾
in body and in mind.
若陛下崩于法兰西
He fears that if His Majesty should die in France,
只怕我国将陷入混乱
he would leave the kingdom in great confusion.
陛下进来可好
How is the King?
传言说他龙体欠佳
There are rumours that he is unwell.
甚至无法再继续领兵带队
That he may be unable to lead the army.
不 大人 陛下定会亲自挂帅出征
Oh no, my Lord. The King will lead his soldiers.
毋需质疑
Make no mistake of that.
事实是
For here is the truth:
陛下不仅希望收复法兰西
The King does not just want France back,
还想重拾他的青春与荣耀
but all of his honour and his youth as well.
我敢这般断言 只因我也有同样的渴望
And, in that, he is like me.
陛下 请允许我向您引见
Your Majesty, may I present
唐璜·埃斯塔班·曼里克·德拉尔
His Highness Don Juan Estaban Manrique de Lara,
奈赫拉公爵殿下
Duke of Najera.
- 殿下 - 陛下
- Your Highness. - Your Majesty.
欢迎来我宫中一聚
I am very happy to receive you at my court.
相信到目前为止 您对一切都还满意吧
I trust you have been well entertained so far?
[西班牙语]满意 他是问我们此次的拜访吗
Está satisfecho de que nos pregunte sobre nuestra visita?
非常满意 我游览了著名的塔楼
Indeed. I have visited the famous Tower
以及泰晤士河
and also the River Thames.
在我眼中
In my opinion, it is not possible
此河之美 举世无双
that a more beautiful river should exist in the world.
- 而且河中还有许多… - 天鹅 殿下
- And with so many... cisnes? - Swans, your Highness.
没错 天鹅
Yes. Swans.
萨里大人还带殿下参观了巴黎园林
My Lord Surrey also took His Highness to the Paris Gardens,
看到了狗熊与狗打架
to see bears fighting with dogs.
然后
And then, in the same place,
他们牵出了一匹小马 背上有只滑稽的猿猴
they brought a pony with an ape on his back!
只见那小马在狗群中乱踢
And to see the animal kicking among the dogs,
而猿猴还在它背上尖叫 着实令人捧腹
with the screams of the ape was very laughable.
公爵殿下
Well, Your Highness, I trust
相信今晚 我貌美如花的娇妻
this evening you will also be well entertained
及我的长女 玛丽女士
by my beautiful wife the Queen
也会让您满意而归
and my first daughter, the Lady Mary.
殿下只想确认
His Highness only desires Your Majesty to confirm
贵国军队是否已准备好入侵法兰西
if your armies are ready for the invasion of France.
我已经做出了承诺
I have already given my word.
殿下还想要我怎样
What more does Your Highness expect of me?
奈赫拉公爵殿下驾到
His Highness, the Duke of Najera.
- 殿下 - 陛下
- Your Highness. - Your Majesty.
这位是玛丽女士
The Lady Mary.
[西班牙语]殿下
Su Alteza.
能将您迎至我父王宫中 实属荣幸
Es un honor darle la bienvenida al Palacio de mi padre.
作为罗马帝国的将军 您的威名家喻户晓
Como general del imperio romano, su nombre es bien conocido.
您会说西班牙语 玛丽小姐
Habla español, Srta. Mary.
略知一二
Un poco de conocimiento.
有其母必有其女 不是吗
Una madre debe tener una hija, no?
这只是巧合吗 正说到战争
So, is it a coincidence that there is talk of war
奈赫拉将军就来了
and then General Najera turns up here at court?
绝对是巧合
Absolutely.
这只是次私人访问
This is a private visit.
殿下是来伦敦观光
His Highness came to London to see the Tower
游塔泛舟
and row on the river
观赏天鹅
and see the swans.
你当我是白痴吗
Do you take me for a fool?
不敢 大使阁下
No, Excellency.
白痴与否 只有咱们自己最清楚
You are what you are. And so am I.
凯特 我不跳舞行吗 拜托
Kat! May I not dance? Please!
你当然能行
Of course you can!
你一定能跳好 小姐
Of course you can dance, my Lady.
莱斯利先生 敢问 关于王后的信仰问题
Mr. Risley, may I ask: what have you heard of
您可有耳闻
the Queen's religious beliefs?
当然是与陛下一致的
They are the same, surely, as His Majesty's?
我着实不敢苟同 我怀疑王后
I think not. Indeed, I suspect Her Majesty
是秘密的新教徒 总有一天我会证明这点
of being a secret Protestant and I intend one day to prove it.
您为此不惜冒险激怒陛下
And in so doing risk the anger of the King?
莱斯利先生 为了我们的信仰
Mr. Risley, for the sake of our faith,
以及我国的未来
and the future of our country
我已做好以身犯险的准备
I am prepared to risk a great deal.
布兹医生 怎么了
Dr. Butts! What is it?
回王后 是陛下的腿
It's the King's leg, Your Majesty.
他的溃疡发作 现在极度痛苦
His ulcer has burst. He is in great pain.
过来
Come.
- 凯瑟琳 - 亲爱的 让我看看
- Catherine! - Dearest, let me see!
不 别看
Please, don't.
还不算最糟
I have seen worse things.
给我片膏药 快
Give me a poultice. Quickly now.
陛下可否稍稍抬腿
If Your Majesty could move your leg...
放在我的腿上
and place it across my lap?
好了 亲爱的 快
There, dearest. Quickly!
只要陛下病体未愈
As long as the King is sick,
我就要一直与他同室而居
I will move my bed to his chamber,
- 以便及时照料 - 遵命 夫人
- the better to look after him. - Madam.
快点
Come on, lads.
我曾上过战场 都是老黄历了
I went to war once, a long time ago.
我们和法国人拼长矛
We broke lances against the French.
古时候的骑士们都那样打仗
The knights did in the old days.
- 可是这次 - 拿稳
- This... - Steady.
这次的战争不同 是枪炮作战
...this is a different war: a war of guns.
- 射得好 - 再来
- Good shot. - Again.
- 射得好 - 有两下子
- Good shooting. - Well done.
- 你叫什么名字 - 理查 公爵大人
- What's your name? - Richard, Your Grace.
- 理查·雷兰 - 理查·雷兰 你即将奔赴战场
- Richard Leland. - You are soon to war, Richard Leland.
下一位
Next.
理查 干得好极了
That was well done, Richard.
我叫哈里 哈里·赫斯特
Harry. Harry Hurst.
- 你要去法国吗 - 我不知道
- Are you coming to France? - I don't know.
- 我枪打得不好 - 那你会什么
- I can't shoot like that. - What can you do?
我是农场工人 我会养牛
I'm a farm labourer, me. I can herd cows,
铲粪 修篱笆
shovel shit, and build fences.
天啊 希望我能有一半的天才 哈里
Christ! I wish I'd half your talent, Harry!
- 谢谢 - 你 下一个
- Thank you. - You there! Next.
陛下
Your Majesty,
爱德华王子殿下驾到
Prince Edward is here.
王后
Madam.
殿下 真高兴见到您
Your Grace. How lovely to see you.
王后 我特来致谢 感谢您送来
Madam, I came to thank you for the outfits of crimson velvet
红色天鹅绒和白缎子的衣服
and white satin you sent me.
你能喜欢 我很高兴
Well, I am very glad that you liked them.
我还要感谢我高贵杰出的父王
I would also like to thank my noble and illustrious father
赐予我的珠宝 但听说父王病了
for the jewels he sent me. But they told me he was sick.
殿下请放心
Well, I am pleased to tell Your Grace
陛下现在好多了
that His Majesty is now much better.
他一定是爱我的 不然的话
He must love me. For if he did not love me,
就不会赐予我诸多赏赐
he would not give me these fine gifts.
他非常爱你 你对他来说
He loves you very much. You are very special
非常特别 我知道 如果有可能
to him and I know that he would like
他愿意经常去看你
to see you more often if he could.
谢谢你
Thank you.
祝您日安 王后
I wish you a good day, Madam.
可怜的孩子
Poor child.
诸位大人
My Lords.
准备得如何 我认为今日有些懈怠
How go our preparations? I think they have gone slackly!
我忍不住怀疑
I'm beginning to suppose
众位是否对战争态度消极
your lordships are not so keen to go to war after all.
请坐
Sit.
陛下 炮架 推车 马车
Majesty, the gun carriages, carts, wagons,
烤箱 马匹 炮兵以及武器
the ovens, horses, artillery, and
都准备就绪 已经装船
ordnance are all made ready and dispatched for shipping.
另将征调300艘船供陛下所用
And a further 300 ships have been requisitioned
将于一月之内到港
for Your Majesty's use and will be in port within the month.
还要等一个月
Within the month!
若非你怠慢渎职 此刻船早该备好
They should be already in port if you had not been so remiss
只待启程
and neglectful in your duties!
公爵 布洛涅的地图准备好吗
Your Grace, what about our maps of Boulogne?
陛下 我们没有地图
Your Majesty, we do not have any maps,
所以我们只能依靠法国间谍徳布伦
so we will have to rely on the advice of a French spy, de Buren.
这么说 我们对战场一无所知
So we are to blunder about in the dark
只能依靠法国间谍的丁点忠诚吗
and trust to the honesty of French spies!
公爵 愿上帝保佑我们
God help us, Your Grace,
你巴不得我们战死
for it seems you have not!
别等什么船了
We will not wait for more ships!
大军十日内乘船进军法国
This army will embark for France in 10 days time,
在加莱登陆 直接开进布洛涅
land in Calais, and straight away march to Boulogne.
攻打巴黎前 我们要用三周拿下此城
We have three weeks to take this town before we proceed on to Paris.
我出征法国之时 由王后陛下
Now, while I am in France, the Queen's Highness,
凯瑟琳王后摄政
Queen Catherine, will act as Regent
全权处理一切事宜
and rule in my stead.
赫福德大人 我怀疑您反对这场战争
Lord Hertford, who I begin to suspect is against this war,
仍为陆军中尉 留守国都
will stay as Lieutenant to the Realm.
如今 我要提醒各位
Now, need I remind your lordships that
此去法国征战 不仅是为了荣誉和骄傲
we go to France not solely for honour and glory,
而是为了捍卫我们的公正权利
but to recover our just rights and inheritances
和从我们手中强行夺走并强占已久的遗产
taken from us by violence and withheld from us for too long.
- 陛下所言甚是 - 陛下圣明
- Yes, Your Majesty. - Your Majesty.
陛下
Your Majesty.
他让王后摄政
He has made the Queen Regent!
- 为何 她对治国毫无经验 - 我也不明白
- Why? She has no knowledge of matters of state! - I do not know.
但据我所知 事实并非如此
But from what I hear of her, I do not think it right.
我想国王应该明白
I think the King should be aware
养虎为患一事
how perilous a matter it is
不容疏忽
to cherish a serpent in one's own bosom.
凯瑟琳 以防我在法国遭遇不测
Catherine, I have to tell you here in order,
我要在此对你下口谕
in case do not come back from France.
简言之 议会会通过新的继承法
Shortly, Parliament will pass a new Act of Succession,
将我的儿子爱德华任命为继承人
naming my son Edward as my heir.
若他发生意外
If he has no issue,
则由玛丽女士继承
then it passes to the Lady Mary
其后为伊丽莎白女士
and then to the Lady Elizabeth.
这是我的心愿
Those are my wishes.
我明白
Understood.
玛丽 别哭
Do not cry, Mary,
我又不是去死
for I do not intend to die.
你保证要经常给我写信
Promise you will write to me often!
告诉我国内发生的一切
Tell me all that happens in my kingdom
写下任何你想说的话
and whatever you see fit to write.
我把孩子们托付给你
I leave my children in your care,
你一定要照顾好他们
knowing that there are not more loving hands in this world.
别了
Farewell.
(法国 布洛涅)
重获新生的感觉很好吧 陛下
It makes you happy to be alive, doesn't it, Majesty?
- 公爵 - 陛下
- Your Grace. - Majesty.
幸会
Well met!
情况如何
How do we prosper?
陛下 关口已经被阻闭
Majesty, the port is blockaded
整个城镇也被基本包围
and the town is already partially invested.
守城官兵自城内紧锁城门
Its gates are shut and its defenders shut inside.
听说法国人自以为固若金汤的堡垒
I have been told the French consider that their strong ramparts
和双层防御城墙可轻易抵挡我们的火炮
and double walls make them invulnerable to our artillery!
那让我们走着瞧
Well, we shall see about that!
我们这次带来的火炮足以荡平幽冥地府
We have brought enough cannon here to conquer hell!
- 驾 - 前进
- Yeah! - Forward!
我几乎不敢相信自己的眼睛 看 理查
I can't believe my eyes! Look, Richard!
英格兰国王 御驾亲临
It's the King of England himself!
- 你有何感想 - 我要是法国人的话
- What do you think? - I reckon if I were the French
现在肯定被吓得屁滚尿流了
I'd be fucking scared.
英格兰的勇士们 今天 你们将会被载入史册
Englishmen, today you have every reason to be proud!
今天 我们吹响了布洛涅战役的号角
Today, we begin our campaign of Boulogne.
- 威武 - 我们曾苦心孤诣 劝以良言
- Yeah! - We have offered terms of peace
只为保有我们的正当权益 夺回我们的遗产
in return for our just rights and inheritances.
- 正当权益 - 无奈敌人利欲熏心
- Just rights! - But our enemy has refused
悍然拒绝归还
to render what they owe us.
他们可知道 勇敢的英格兰人
They should know that we do not
从不缺乏为求正义而拼死抗战的决心
lack the courage to fight to the death for justice.
这片曾被敌人铁骑践踏过的土地
These lands were taken from us by violence
- 今日要插满我们的旌旗 - 遍插旌旗
- and I mean to have them back. - We'll take them back!
为扬吾王威 为英格兰 为圣乔治 奋战到底
For King Henry, for England, and for St. George!
吾王万岁
Long live the King!
为英格兰而战
For England!
不要射击
Ne tirez pas encore!
躲在城墙后面
Reculez derriere les murs!
准备火炮
Prepare your fire!
士兵 各就各位
Solders, to your stations!
第一队指挥官 列阵以待
Section One Commander! Prepare your guns!
第一队 列阵以待
Section One, prepare your guns!
第二队指挥官 列阵以待
Section Two Commander! Prepare your guns!
火炮装弹
Load your cannon!
- 列阵以待 - 准备完毕
- Prepare your guns! - Ready, guns.
第三队指挥官 列阵以待
Section Three Commander! Prepare your guns!
- 火药桶 - 士兵 进入战壕 - 快步行进
- Ram barrel! - Soldiers, into the trenches! - Quick march!
第二队指挥官 带上你的士兵
Section Two Commander, take both your men!
- 第三队指挥官 准备好了报告 - 遵命
- Section Three Commander, report when ready. - Yes, sir!
- 第三队准备完毕 - 准备完毕 长官
- Section Three ready. - That's ready, sir.
所有火炮枪支对准城堡和城门
All guns take aim for the gates and castle.
第一队 瞄准
Section One, take aim!
- 各指挥官 - 瞄准
- Section Commanders! - Take aim!
再次确认目标
Confirm you have your target!
- 第三队 瞄准 - 第一队 确认目标完毕
- Section Three, take aim. - Section One, target ready.
第二队 确认目标
Section Two, confirm target.
- 第二队 准备完毕 - 第二队确认目标 瞄准
- Section Two, ready! - Section Two has target, sir. Take aim!
- 第三队 确认目标 - 第三队确认完毕
- Section Three, confirm. - Section Three ready.
保持队形 听我命令再开火
Hold sections! Hold fire until I give the order!
列队 士兵
Let's go, men.
- 准备开火 列队 - 准备开火 - 列队
- Hold fire! Move! - Hold your fire! - Move!
- 准备开火 - 相时而动
- Hold your fire! - Easy for the time!
- 看看它到底有多坚固 - 各就各位
- Now we'll see how invulnerable it really is! - In position!
准备完毕 长官
Ready, captain!
第一队 开火
Section one, fire!
- 扬吾王威 - 准备 - 准备
- For the King! - Ready! - Ready!
全体注意 开火
All sections, fire!
第一队 开火
Section One, fire!
开火 开火 开火
fire!fire!fire!
准备
Ready!
装弹
Charge the gun!
- 英格兰 - 万岁 - 英格兰
- England! - England! - England!
为英格兰而战
For England!
回撤原位 装填弹药
Back into position! Reload all guns!
如你见到赫福德大人 把这个交给他
If you could see that this is delivered to my Lord Hertford.
- 多谢 - 遵命 陛下
- Thank you. - Majesty.
陛下 拉蒂默先生来了
Madam, here is Mr. Latimer.
你好 阁下
Your Grace.
陛下 我已不能再使用那个头衔
Alas, Madam, I am no longer entitled to such an address.
我被加德纳大主教剥去了主教之职
I was deprived of my bishopric by Bishop Gardiner.
我知道 同时我也了解当前的境况
I know. And I know the circumstances of it.
但我仍有意聘用你为我这里的私人牧师
Still, I have a mind to appoint you chaplain to my household.
此话当真吗 陛下
Are you absolutely sure, my Lady?
您一定清楚我当下的身份
You must know my reputation.
拉蒂默先生 你是一名神职人员
Your reputation, Mr. Latimer, is of a man of the Gospels
也是虔诚的基督徒
and a true Christian.
举例来说吧 你会否觉得
For example, do you suppose that it is a bad thing
如果全英格兰的子民都去研读圣经
that everyone in England should be able to
将会是一件坏事吗
read the Bible for themselves?
不 恰恰相反
No. On the contrary,
我相信那会是非常重要的事情
I believe it to be a vital thing.
没有了上帝的指引 我们将变得无知
For without God's direct word we that be unlettered
困惑并且黯淡无光
remain confused and without grace.
即便一些人鼓吹研读圣经
Even though some would say
会导致异端邪说也不能动摇你吗
that the reading of the Bible leads to heresy?
倘若真有人这么说 他们便是在
If they say so, then they are
用人类的罪恶之心
wickedly charging the holy sanctified word of God
挑战上帝神圣的权柄与教化
with the offences of man.
没错 人们怎会因见他人饱食无度
You are right. Do people deny themselves food,
便要自己忍饥废食
because they see others overeat?
又怎会因见邻屋毁于火难
Or avoid using fire because
便要自家弃柴避火
they have seen a neighbour's house burn down?
多么愚昧无知 拉蒂默先生
Oh blind ignorance, Mr. Latimer,
用人类的罪忖 诽谤上帝的神圣
to slander God for man's offences.
陛下 如果您仍有意聘用我的话
Madam, if you are still of a mind to have me,
在下当全力以赴
I will most joyfully be your chaplain.
谢谢你
I thank you.
我有一事相求
I have one favour,
你一定要对玛丽女士
which is that you conceal the true workings
隐瞒你于此所传播的真正教义
of your mind from the Lady Mary.
在此世间没有任何事情
For nothing in this world will
能改变她对其母信仰的笃忠
change her allegiance to the faith of her mother,
我亦对此十分尊重
and I respect her for that.
陛下 承蒙您信任
Madam, believe me,
我与陛下的子女
I shall be the soul of discretion in my dealings with
以及宫中人士打交道时
all His Majesty's children,
定会过从谨慎
and with the world.
多谢
Thank you.
夫人
My Lady.
姐姐
Sister,
您确信拉蒂默先生真的可靠吗
are you sure you can really trust Mr. Latimer's discretion?
有句话不知当将不当讲
I know I should not say so to Your Majesty,
但我恐他出尔反尔
but I fear his appointment.
此刻我怎能畏首畏尾
Should I play the coward?
安 你也知道嫁给国王绝非我愿
Anne, you know that I never wanted to marry the King.
但既已如此
But since I had to,
我理应在其位谋其政
I may at least use what influence I now possess
为我心仪之信仰谋福
to further the cause that I believe in with all my heart.
宗教改革势在必行
The cause of the Reformation!
这样才能肃清异端
Then at least I can address my God
虔心追随我主荣光
with a clear conscience and an honest soul.
安 你一定要支持我
Please say that you understand, Anne!
求你了
Please.
快速前进 左 右
Forward! Come on! Left, right.
保持队型
There we are!
- 见鬼 - 不会一直下下去的
- Shit! - It can't last forever.
兄弟们 这边
Lads, come here!
- 快 - 大家快走
- Come on! - Move on, men!
大人 这边请
This way, my Lord.
- 陛下 特雷维索先生求见 - 吉洛拉摩
- Your Majesty, Senor Treviso. - Girolamo.
陛下
Your Majesty.
过来 说说你们打算如何打通地道
Come, show me where you intend to dig these mines.
臣预计挖三条地道
I intend to dig three tunnels.
其中两个为明修栈道 暗度陈仓之用
Two will be a diversion, to confuse the enemy.
真正在这里 城墙旁边
The main one will be here, at the town wall,
地道直达城堡之下
which will lead directly under the castle.
- 用时多少 - 这要依情况而定
- How long will it take? - That depends on many things:
土质 溢水 诸如此类
The type of ground, danger of flooding, and so on.
敌方城墙的地基深度亦尤为重要
Also, how far into the earth they have built the walls.
但依臣之见 三周之内
But I say we could be under the castle
我方可将地道通至城堡 爆破城门
and able to detonate a huge explosion in three weeks.
特雷维索先生 两周
Two weeks, Senor Treviso!
给你两周
Two weeks!
人手任你调遣
Take the troops you need.
大伙拼命点干
Put your backs into it, men.
我方进展神速
We are making excellent progress.
但我想知道罗马皇帝方面战况如何
But I want to know how the Emperor is doing
毕竟我们是联袂作战
since we are in this war together.
回陛下 罗马皇帝所率军队目前
Majesty, the Emperor's forces are at present besieging
正围攻卢森堡和圣埃蒂安
the fortresses of Luxembourg and St. Didier.
我方自有神助 定能早日破城
With God's help, we will break our siege first
进军巴黎
and then advance on Paris.
我方强大火力已让敌方死伤惨重
With the damage our guns are already inflicting,
臣保证拿下布洛涅已指日可待
I swear Boulogne will not hold out for long.
依我看 法国人自以为
I think that the French were foolish
城墙坚不可摧简直愚蠢之极
to think that their walls were invincible.
他们还没见识过我们大炮的厉害
They had not seen our guns.
轻点跟上
Avancez. Doucement.
九月进攻巴黎 再好不过
Paris by September! Good,
巴黎有不少我欲除之而后快的人
there are a lot of Frenchmen in Paris I would like to kill,
如此一来他们的如花美眷全都唯我是用
so I can sleep with their wives with a clear conscience!
各位大人
Gentlemen
- 干 - 干
- Salut! - Salut!
- 陛下 - 什么事
- Majesty. - What is it?
大人 南城门外发现法国人踪迹
The French! They've broken out beyond the southern gate, sir.
我去看看
I'll go!
大人 我令你率大军封锁各个城门
Your Grace! I want you to cover all the gates with a massive force,
- 以防调虎离山之计 - 遵旨
- in case this is a diversion. Go! - Majesty.
哪里去了
Where are they?
我以国王之名命令你停下
Arrêtez! Revenez au nom du roi!
那边 抓住他
There, there! Get him!
我奉国王之命令你束手就擒
Stop in the name of the King!
停下
Arrêtez!
- 人呢 - 跑到沟下面了
- Where is he? - He's down in the ditch!
大家小心为上
Keep your wits about you.
掩护
Take cover!
趴下
Stay down!
- 看见人了吗 - 两人已死
- Do you see him? - Two on the ground!
冲啊
A l'attaqué!
准备 杀啊
Ready! Let's go!
大人
Your Grace,
我虽无需帮助 但还是感谢您出手相救
I didn't need your help but thank you all the same.
跟上 誓死捍卫布洛涅 冲啊
Suivez-moi! Pour Boulogne! A l'attaque!
这些你来对付怎样
Shall I leave them to you then?
纳命来
Ah! Here we come!
为了英格兰 冲啊
For England!
父亲 父亲
Papa! Papa!
父亲 快醒醒
Papa! Papa! Papa, roveille-toi!
快睁开眼啊
Allez, ouvre tes yeux!
小姐
Mademoiselle?
装弹药
Load cannon!
- 将军 - 保持直线 挖这里
- General. - Keep the lines straight. Dig in there.
我给你带了些吃的
I've brought you some food.
[西班牙语]我不饿
No tengo hambre.
你父亲还活着
Your father is still alive.
真的吗
Is that true?
他虽身受重伤 但我们正在全力救治
He was wounded but we're taking care of him.
- 我能见他吗 - 很快 我保证
- Can I see him? - Soon. I promise.
都给我卖力点 枪杆子都给我端起来
Put your backs into it. Roll that barrel!
敢问芳名
What's your name?
布丽吉特·罗塞洛
Brigitte, Brigitte Rousselot.
快点
Look lively.
吃点东西吧
You should eat.
你们为什么非要入侵我们
Why are you here? In France?
- 这里不属于你们 - 但曾是我国领土
- This isn't your country. - It used to be.
我们都曾祖居伊甸
And we all used to live in Eden.
难道也要再夺回来不成
It doesn't mean we can go back again!
你为什么不放了我
Why won't you release me?
那不就放虎归山了吗
So you can go on fighting against us?
没错 这样我就能亲自手刃你
Yes! So I can go on killing you.
此言差矣 小姐
No, Mademoiselle.
你现在可是我的阶下囚
You're my prisoner now.
或许我还能借你换一笔赎金
Perhaps I'll even get a ransom for you!
我想问城里情况如何
Can I ask how things are in the town?
城内粮草充足与否
Do people have enough food?
守城足矣 大人无须担忧
They have plenty! You shouldn't worry about them.
投降绝无可能
They'll never surrender.
尤其对你的国王 那个基督的怪物
Not to that sacred monster, your King.
你说怪物
Monster?
是的 怪物
Oui! Un monstre!
我们称他是英国的尼禄(古罗马暴君)
You know we call him the English Nero!
没听说过吗
Didn't you know that?
万福吾主 丧失信仰之人 必遭灾祸
Dominus tecum. Benedicta tu in mulieribus,
吾主慈悲 泽被众生
et benedictus fructus ventris tui.
- 莱斯利先生 - 主教阁下
- Mr. Risley. - Your Grace,
我有些消息 也许您会感兴趣
I have some news I thought you might be interested in.
据说凯瑟琳王后已经任命
It seems Queen Catherine has
休·拉蒂默为她的私人牧师
appointed Hugh Latimer as her private Chaplain.
消息是否属实
Are you sure?
是
Yes.
居然还有人赞她冰雪聪明
And I thought someone said she was an intelligent woman!
地道进展如何 哈里
How's the tunnelling, Harry?
我们已经掘了五十步长
We've dug about 50 paces.
真不是人干的活儿 全都是黏土
It's bloody hard work; and there's a lot of clay.
黏土还好 若是沙子
I prefer the clay. It's not like sand.
随时都会流下来 活埋了我们
Always afraid it's gonna collapse and bury you.
你那边怎样
How've you been?
有个法国军官时常露面
There's a French officer comes out sometimes.
在城垛上逗留片刻
He stands for a few moments on the castle rampart,
观察我们 然后走回去
looking at us. Then he goes back inside.
- 我只用开一枪 就能要他小命 - 是啊
- I just need one good shot. One good shot. - Aye.
喂 听说了吗
Hey, have you heard?
军帐附近来了几个女人
There are meant to be a few women around camp.
倒是不多 只有几个 我听说的
Not many, mind. Just a few. That's what I heard.
想得性病就去吧
If you fancy the pox!
是啊 也许你说得对
Aye. Perhaps you're right.
话说回来 我老家有妻子 她有孕在身
In any case, I have a wife back home and she is with child.
你想要儿子还是女儿
Oh! What do you want a boy or girl?
儿子
A boy.
愿上帝保佑我们能快点回家
I hope to God we're not here too long.
陛下亲征 时日不长
Although Your Majesty's absence has not been long,
然臣妾日思夜想
yet the want of your presence
寝食难安 茶饭不思
means that I cannot take pleasure in anything
惟盼陛下鸿雁传书
until I hear from Your Majesty.
臣妾度日如年 所为牵肠挂肚
Time hangs heavily. I have a great desire to know
惟陛下之近况
how Your Majesty has done since you left.
只求陛下平安无恙
For your prosperity and health
妾身如何当无关紧要
I prefer and desire more than my own.
臣妾虽知陛下出宫
And although I know Your Majesty's absence
皆为操劳国家大事
is never without great need
然人非草木 思君之情 难以自抑
still, love and affection compel me to desire your presence.
陛下待臣妾之情深意重
Thus love makes me set aside my own convenience and pleasure for you,
纵千言万语不能言表
at whose hands I have received so much love
臣妾无以为报 惟全心侍奉
and goodness that words cannot express it.
听闻天气恶劣 延误征程 陛下甚为忧心
We hear word of ill weather and delays besetting you.
然龙体安康 实乃大幸
And though we thank God for your good health,
臣妾恭候佳音
we anxiously await the joyous news
遥祝陛下此番大获全胜
of the success of your great venture
平安凯旋
and for your safe and triumphant return.
下面多放些桶
More buckets down there!
举国上下日日祈祷
For which all England offers daily prayers.
这里多放些支撑物
More supports in the space!
陛下命臣妾代理朝纲
I fear I am but a poor substitute for Your Majesty
只怕有心无力 难以胜任
in the matter of the guidance of your kingdom.
惟愿陛下早日回宫
I long for your return.
愿神保佑陛下
I commit you to God's care and governance.
您卑微的
By Your Majesty's humble,
妻子 仆人 凯瑟琳王后
obedient wife and servant, Catherine the Queen.
恳请陛下再宽限几日
But, Majesty, I beg you to give us a little more time.
士兵们不眠不休 日夜赶工
The men are working all day and all night.
有时不得已停止挖掘 加固洞顶
But sometimes we must stop digging to support the roof
防止塌方
or else everything collapses.
医官
Master Surgeon!
- 请便 特雷维索先生 - 陛下 臣告退
- Senor Treviso. - Your Majesty.
- 何事 - 陛下
- What is it? - Majesty,
近来有十名士兵丧命 臣深感遗憾
I regret to inform you of the deaths of ten of your soldiers.
- 无非因伤阵亡 - 非也 陛下
- Soldier die of their wounds. - No, Your Majesty.
他们均死于血痢
The men all died of the bloody flux.
- 痢疾吗 - 是的 陛下
- Dysentery? - Yes, Your Majesty.
臣担心此种疾病会在全军
I am afraid that there is an outbreak of the disease
蔓延开来
throughout your army.
天知道会死多少人
God alone knows how many it will take away.
退下 医官
Master Surgeon.
- 特雷维索先生 - 恭送陛下
- Mr. Treviso. - Majesty.
恭送陛下
Your Majesty.
我有话要问你
Let me ask you something:
你如何看待那位意大利绅士
What do you think of our Italian gentleman,
吉洛拉摩·特雷维索先生
Senor Girolamo Treviso?
修地道那家伙
The builder of tunnels.
- 此话何意 - 你相信他吗
- What do you mean? - I mean do you trust him?
为何不相信他
Why should I not trust him?
只是我偶然听闻
It's only that I happen to know that, some time ago,
他曾说会造一面足够大的镜子
he said he could build a mirror large enough
将其置于多佛的崖壁上
that if set upon the cliffs of Dover
陛下便能从中窥到
His Majesty would be able to see,
在布洛涅港口
reflected in it, the movement of French ships
出入的法国船只
in and out of the port of Boulogne.
阁下明白我的意思吗
Do you see what I mean, Your Grace?
你觉得他疯了吗
Do you think he's mad?
阁下自有判断
It's only a suggestion.
不过 非他一人如此
But then, he's not the only one!
换岗
Change the watch!
夜巡换岗
Change the night watch!
- 小组待命 - 拉我上去
- Section ready! - Pull me up!
准备完毕 长官
Ready captain!